<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trade - Tag - My economics study notes</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/trade/</link>
    <description>My economics study notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.153.0 &amp; FixIt v0.4.1</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/trade/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Openness, Government Size and the Terms of Trade</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/022-epifaniopennessgovernmentsize2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/022-epifaniopennessgovernmentsize2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper investigates the relationship between trade openness and the size of governments, both theoretically and empirically. We argue that openness can increase the size of governments through two channels: (1) a terms-of-trade externality, whereby trade lowers the domestic cost of taxation, and (2) the demand for insurance, whereby trade raises risk and public transfers. We provide a unified framework for studying and testing these two mechanisms. Our main theoretical prediction is that the relative strength of the two explanations depends on a key parameter, namely, the elasticity of substitution between domestic and foreign goods. Moreover, while the first mechanism is inefficient from the standpoint of world welfare, the second, instead, is optimal. In the empirical part of the paper, we provide new evidence on the positive association between openness and government size and we explore its determinants. Consistent with the terms-of-trade externality channel, we show that the correlation is contingent on a low elasticity of substitution between domestic and foreign goods. Our findings raise warnings that globalization may have led to inefficiently large governments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Labour Market Regulations and the Sectoral Reallocation of Workers: The Case of Trade Reforms</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/046-kambourovlabourmarketregulations2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/046-kambourovlabourmarketregulations2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this paper I highlight the importance of incorporating the institutional features of local labour markets into the analysis of trade reforms. A trade reform is often deemed beneficial because the elimination of trade barriers allows labour to reallocate towards those sectors in the economy in which the country has a comparative advantage. The amount and speed of the reallocation, however, and the post-reform behaviour of output, productivity and welfare, will depend on how regulated the labour market is. First, I document that high firing costs slow down the intersectoral reallocation of labour after a trade reform. Second, in order to isolate the effect of firing costs on labour reallocation, output and welfare after a trade reform, I build a dynamic general equilibrium model. I find that if a country does not liberalize its labour market at the outset of its trade reform, the intersectoral reallocation of workers will be 30% slower, and as much as 30% of the gains in real output and labour productivity in the years following the trade reform will be lost. From a policy standpoint, the message is that while trade reforms are desirable, they need to be complemented by labour market reforms in order to be fully successful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Market Size, Trade, and Productivity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2008/011-melitzmarketsizetrade2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2008/011-melitzmarketsizetrade2008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We develop a monopolistically competitive model of trade with firm heterogeneity &amp;ndash; in terms of productivity differences &amp;ndash; and endogenous differences in the &amp;ldquo;toughness&amp;rdquo; of competition across markets &amp;ndash; in terms of the number and average productivity of competing firms. We analyse how these features vary across markets of different size that are not perfectly integrated through trade; we then study the effects of different trade liberalization policies. In our model, market size and trade affect the toughness of competition, which then feeds back into the selection of heterogeneous producers and exporters in that market. Aggregate productivity and average mark-ups thus respond to both the size of a market and the extent of its integration through trade (larger, more integrated markets exhibit higher productivity and lower mark-ups). Our model remains highly tractable, even when extended to a general framework with multiple asymmetric countries integrated to different extents through asymmetric trade costs. We believe this provides a useful modelling framework that is particularly well suited to the analysis of trade and regional integration policy scenarios in an environment with heterogeneous firms and endogenous mark-ups.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Make Trade Not War?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2008/033-martinmaketradenot2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2008/033-martinmaketradenot2008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper analyses theoretically and empirically the relationship between military conflicts and trade. We show that the conventional wisdom that trade promotes peace is only partially true even in a model where trade is economically beneficial, military conflicts reduce trade, and leaders are rational. When war can occur because of the presence of asymmetric information, the probability of escalation is lower for countries that trade more bilaterally because of the opportunity cost associated with the loss of trade gains. However, countries more open to global trade have a higher probability of war because multilateral trade openness decreases bilateral dependence to any given country and the cost of a bilateral conflict. We test our predictions on a large data set of military conflicts on the 1950-2000 period. Using different strategies to solve the endogeneity issues, including instrumental variables, we find robust evidence for the contrasting effects of bilateral and multilateral trade openness. For proximate countries, we find that trade has had a surprisingly large effect on their probability of military conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trading Population for Productivity: Theory and Evidence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2008/044-galortradingpopulationproductivity2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2008/044-galortradingpopulationproductivity2008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This research argues that the differential effect of international trade on the demand for human capital across countries has been a major determinant of the distribution of income and population across the globe. In developed countries the gains from trade have been directed towards investment in education and growth in income per capita, whereas a significant portion of these gains in less developed economies has been chanelled towards population growth. Cross-country regressions establish that indeed trade has positive effects on fertility and negative effects on education in non-OECD economies, while inducing fertility decline and human capital formation in OECD economies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Advantage and Heterogeneous Firms</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/002-bernardcomparativeadvantageheterogeneous2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/002-bernardcomparativeadvantageheterogeneous2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper examines how country, industry, and firm characteristics interact in general equilibrium to determine nations&amp;rsquo; responses to trade liberalization. When firms possess heterogeneous productivity, countries differ in relative factor abundance, and industries vary in factor intensity, falling trade costs induce reallocations of resources both within and across industries and countries. These reallocations generate substantial job turnover in all sectors, spur relatively more creative destruction in comparative advantage industries than in comparative disadvantage industries, and magnify ex ante comparative advantage to create additional welfare gains from trade. The improvements in aggregate productivity as countries liberalize dampen and can even reverse the real-wage losses of scarce factors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Icebergs: Towards a Theory of Biased Globalization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/009-matsuyamaicebergstheorybiased2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/009-matsuyamaicebergstheorybiased2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast to domestic trade, international trade inherently requires more intensive use of skilled labour with expertise in areas such as international business, language skills, and maritime insurance, and the transoceanic transportation is more capital intensive than the local transportation. In the presence of such bias in factor demands, globalization caused by an improvement in the export technologies can lead to a worldwide increase in the relative prices of the factors used intensively in international trade. Furthermore, a worldwide increase in the factors used intensively in international trade can lead to globalization. To capture these effects, we develop a flexible approach to model costly international trade, which includes the standard iceberg approach as a special case. More specifically, we extend the Ricardian model of trade with a continuum of goods by introducing multiple factors of production and by making technologies of supplying goods depend on whether the destination is home or abroad. If the technologies of supplying the same good to the two destinations differ only in total factor productivity, the model becomes isomorphic to the Ricardian model with the iceberg cost. By allowing the two technologies to differ in the factor intensities, our approach enables us to examine the links between factor endowments, factor prices, and globalization that cannot be captured by the iceberg approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Institutional Quality and International Trade</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/028-levchenkoinstitutionalqualityinternational2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/028-levchenkoinstitutionalqualityinternational2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Institutions &amp;ndash; quality of contract enforcement, property rights, shareholder protection, and the likehave received a great deal of attention in recent years. Yet trade theory has not considered the implications of institutional differences, beyond treating them simply as different technologies or taxes. The purpose of this paper is twofold. First, we propose a simple model of international trade in which institutional differences are modelled within the framework of incomplete contracts. We show that doing so reverses many of the conclusions obtained by equating institutions with productivity. Institutional differences as a source of comparative advantage imply, among other things, that the less developed country may not gain from trade and factor prices may actually diverge as a result of trade. Second, we test empirically whether institutions act as a source of trade, using data on U.S. imports disaggregated by country and industry. The empirical results provide evidence of &amp;ldquo;institutional content of trade&amp;rdquo;: institutional differences are an important determinant of trade flows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Border Mergers as Instruments of Comparative Advantage</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/043-nearycrossbordermergersinstruments2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/043-nearycrossbordermergersinstruments2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A two-country model of oligopoly in general equilibrium is used to show how changes in market structure accompany the process of trade and capital-market liberalization. The model predicts that bilateral mergers in which low-cost firms buy out higher-cost foreign rivals are profitable under Cournot competition. As a result, trade liberalization can trigger international merger waves, in the process encouraging countries to specialize and trade more in accordance with comparative advantage. With symmetric countries, welfare is likely to rise, though the distribution of income always shifts towards profits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outsourcing in a Global Economy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2005/007-grossmanoutsourcingglobaleconomy2005/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2005/007-grossmanoutsourcingglobaleconomy2005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the determinants of the location of subcontracted activity in a general equilibrium model of outsourcing and trade. We model outsourcing as an activity that requires search for a partner and relationship-specific investments that are governed by incomplete contracts. The extent of international outsourcing depends inter alia on the thickness of the domestic and foreign market for input suppliers, the relative cost of searching in each market, the relative cost of customizing inputs and the nature of the contracting environment in each country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Balance Sheet Effects, Bailout Guarantees and Financial Crises</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2004/036-schneiderbalancesheeteffects2004/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2004/036-schneiderbalancesheeteffects2004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper provides a model of boom-bust episodes in middle-income countries. It is based on sectoral differences in corporate finance: the nontradables sector is special in that it faces a contract enforceability problem and enjoys bailout guarantees. As a result, currency mismatch and borrowing constraints arise endogenously in that sector. This sectoral asymmetry allows the model to replicate the main features of observed boom-bust episodes. In particular, episodes begin with a lending boom and a real appreciation, peak in a self-fulfilling crisis during which a real depreciation coincides with widespread bankruptcies, and end in a recession and credit crunch. The nontradables sector accounts for most of the volatility in output and credit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patterns of Skill Premia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2003/008-acemoglupatternsskillpremia2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2003/008-acemoglupatternsskillpremia2003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper develops a model to analyse how skill premia differ over time and across countries, and uses this model to study the impact of international trade on wage inequality. Skill premia are determined by technology, the relative supply of skills, and trade. Technology is itself endogenous, and responds to profit incentives. An increase in the relative supply of skills, holding technology constant, reduces the skill premium. But an increase in the supply of skills over time also induces a change in technology, increasing the demand for skills. The most important result of the paper is that increased international trade induces skill-biased technical change. As a result, trade opening can cause a rise in inequality both in the U.S. and the less developed countries, and thanks to the induced skill-biased technical change, this can happen without a rise in the relative prices of skill-intensive goods in the U.S., which is the usual intervening mechanism in the standard trade models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foreign Direct Investment and Exports with Growing Demand</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2003/025-robforeigndirectinvestment2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2003/025-robforeigndirectinvestment2003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We explore entry into a foreign market with uncertain demand growth. A multinational can serve the foreign demand by two modes, or by a combination thereof: it can export its products, or it can create productive capacity via foreign direct investment (FDI). The advantage of FDI is that it allows for lower marginal cost than exporting does. The disadvantage is that FDI is irreversible and, hence, entails the risk of creating under-utilized capacity in the case that the market turns out to be small. The presence of demand uncertainty and irreversibility gives rise to an interior solution, where the multinational, under certain conditions, both exports its products and does FDI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Price Stability in Open Economies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2003/030-benignopricestabilityopen2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2003/030-benignopricestabilityopen2003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper studies the theoretical conditions under which price stability is the optimal policy in a two-country open-economy model with imperfect competition and price stickiness. Special conditions on the levels of country-specific distortionary taxation and the intratemporal and intertemporal elasticities of substitution need to be satisfied. These restrictions apply to both cooperative and non-cooperative settings. Importantly, we show that cooperative and non-cooperative solutions do not coincide despite market completeness and producer currency pricing. We study the conditions under which quadratic approximations of single countries&amp;rsquo; welfare can be correctly evaluated by relying only on log-linear approximations of the equilibrium conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trade Liberalization, Exit, and Productivity Improvements: Evidence from Chilean Plants</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/010-pavcniktradeliberalizationexit2002/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/010-pavcniktradeliberalizationexit2002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper empirically investigates the effects of liberalized trade on plant productivity in the case of Chile. Chile presents an interesting setting to study this relationship since it underwent a massive trade liberalization that significantly exposed its plants to competition from abroad during the late 1970s and early 1980s. Methodologically, I approach this question in two steps. In the first step, I estimate a production function to obtain a measure of plant productivity. I estimate the production function semiparametrically to correct for the presence of selection and simultaneity biases in the estimates of the input coefficients required to construct a productivity measure. I explicitly incorporate plant exit in the estimation to correct for the selection problem induced by liquidated plants. These methodological aspects are important in obtaining a reliable plant-level productivity measure based on consistent estimates of the input coefficients. In the second step, I identify the impact of trade on plants&amp;rsquo; productivity in a regression framework allowing variation in productivity over time and across traded- and nontraded-goods sectors. Using plant-level panel data on Chilean manufacturers, I find evidence of within plant productivity improvements that can be attributed to a liberalized trade for the plants in the import-competing sector. In many cases, aggregate productivity improvements stem from the reshuffling of resources and output from less to more efficient producers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradualism in Trade Agreements with Asymmetric Countries</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/015-bondgradualismtradeagreements2002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/015-bondgradualismtradeagreements2002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper uses recursive methods to characterize the payoff frontier of self-enforcing trade agreements between countries of asymmetric size. We show that at points on the frontier where only one country&amp;rsquo;s incentive constraint binds, the efficient agreement will be a non-stationary one that starts with a positive trade distortion but eventually reaches free trade. Our analysis illustrates how (i) relative country size, (ii) consumption smoothing incentives, and (iii) sunk investments affect the form of efficient trade agreements. In contrast to previous work on gradualism, our results are obtained from a model in which the economic environment is stationary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimum Tariffs and Retaliation Revisited: How Country Size Matters</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/028-syropoulosoptimumtariffsretaliation2002/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/028-syropoulosoptimumtariffsretaliation2002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his seminal work on tariff retaliation, Johnson (Review of Economic Studies, 21, 1953-1954) showed that a country will &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; a bilateral &amp;ldquo;tariff war&amp;rdquo; if its relative monopoly/monopsony power in world trade is sufficiently large. However, it is unclear from Johnson&amp;rsquo;s analysis and from subsequent research on the subject how this power is determined in general economic environments. An important goal of this paper is to address this issue. With the help of a neoclassical trade model in which country size is at centre stage, it is shown that a sufficient condition for a country to prefer a non-cooperative Nash tariff equilibrium (retaliation) over free trade is that its relative size be sufficiently large. The paper also refines the structure of the general trade model and generates additional characterization results on the importance of country size for best-response tariff functions, retaliatory tariffs, and welfare.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redistribution, Fiscal Competition, and the Politics of Economic Integration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/034-kesslerredistributionfiscalcompetition2002/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2002/034-kesslerredistributionfiscalcompetition2002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The paper examines the consequences of the economic integration of factor markets in a model with two countries that redistribute income among their residents. The social benefits in each country are financed by a source based tax on capital which is democratically chosen by its inhabitants. If either capital or labour is internationally mobile, the countries engage in fiscal competition and the partial integration of capital or labour markets is detrimental to the countries&amp;rsquo; redistributive ability. A move from partial to full integration, however, may alleviate rather than intensify fiscal competition, particularly, if the two countries face sufficiently similar economic and political conditions. In such a situation, for example, tax competition for mobile capital is softened as the labour market becomes more integrated and even vanishes if both factors are fully mobile. As a result, there is more redistribution in equilibrium and a majority of the population in each country is strictly better off.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>International Trade and Currency Exchange</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2001/019-reyinternationaltradecurrency2001/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2001/019-reyinternationaltradecurrency2001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the international scene, away from national legal rules, the use of different currencies is largely due to the operation of the &amp;ldquo;Invisible Hand&amp;rdquo;. The paper develops a three-country model of the world economy. This links real trade patterns with currency exchange structures in a general equilibrium framework which includes transaction costs on foreign exchange markets. In the presence of strategic complementarities, there are multiple equilibrium structures of currency exchange for a given underlying real trade pattern. The existence conditions of these different equilibria are characterized, using the trade links between countries as the key parameters. Finally, repercussions on world output of the choice of a currency exchange structure are analysed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
