<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Time Series - Tag - My economics study notes</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/time-series/</link>
    <description>My economics study notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.153.0 &amp; FixIt v0.4.1</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/time-series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Valid Inference in Partially Unstable Generalized Method of Moments Models</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/012-livalidinferencepartially2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/012-livalidinferencepartially2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper considers time series Generalized Method of Moments (GMM) models where a subset of the parameters are time varying. We focus on an empirically relevant case with moderately large instabilities, which are well approximated by a local asymptotic embedding that does not allow the instability to be detected with certainty, even in the limit. We show that for many forms of the instability and a large class of GMM models, usual GMM inference on the subset of stable parameters is asymptotically unaffected by the partial instability. In the empirical analysis of presumably stable parameters &amp;ndash; such as structural parameters in Euler conditions &amp;ndash; one can thus ignore moderate instabilities in other parts of the model and still obtain approximately correct inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural Changes, Common Stochastic Trends, and Unit Roots in Panel Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/017-baistructuralchangescommon2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/017-baistructuralchangescommon2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper studies the problem of unit root testing in the presence of multiple structural changes and common dynamic factors. Structural breaks represent infrequent regime shifts, while dynamic factors capture common shocks underlying the comovement of economic time series. We examine the modified Sargan-Bhargava (MSB) test in the panel data setting and propose ways to handle multiple structural changes and dynamic factors. Properties of the MSB test under these non-standard conditions are derived. For example, the test statistics are shown to be invariant, in the limit, to mean breaks. This invariance does not carry over to breaks in linear trends, where the test statistics will converge to functionals of weighted Brownian bridges. A simplified test statistic is then proposed, which is invariant to both mean and trend breaks. We further study pooled test statistic based on standardization and combination of $p$-values. Response surfaces for $p$-values of all test statistics are computed to facilitate the empirical implementation of the proposed methodology. The pooled tests are shown to have good finite sample performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting and Predicting Forecast Breakdowns</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/023-giacominidetectingpredictingforecast2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2009/023-giacominidetectingpredictingforecast2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose a theoretical framework for assessing whether a forecast model estimated over one period can provide good forecasts over a subsequent period. We formalize this idea by defining a forecast breakdown as a situation in which the out-of-sample performance of the model, judged by some loss function, is significantly worse than its in-sample performance. Our framework, which is valid under general conditions, can be used not only to detect past forecast breakdowns but also to predict future ones. We show that main causes of forecast breakdowns are instabilities in the data-generating process and relate the properties of our forecast breakdown test to those of structural break tests. The empirical application finds evidence of a forecast breakdown in the Phillips&amp;rsquo; curve forecasts of U.S. inflation, and links it to inflation volatility and to changes in the monetary policy reaction function of the Fed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimation and Forecasting in Models with Multiple Breaks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/027-koopestimationforecastingmodels2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2007/027-koopestimationforecastingmodels2007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper develops a new approach to change-point modelling that allows the number of changepoints in the observed sample to be unknown. The model we develop assumes that regime durations have a Poisson distribution. It approximately nests the two most common approaches: the time-varying parameter (TVP) model with a change-point every period and the change-point model with a small number of regimes. We focus considerable attention on the construction of reasonable hierarchical priors both for regime durations and for the parameters that characterize each regime. A Markov chain Monte Carlo posterior sampler is constructed to estimate a version of our model, which allows for change in conditional means and variances. We show how real-time forecasting can be done in an efficient manner using sequential importance sampling. Our techniques are found to work well in an empirical exercise involving U.S. GDP growth and inflation. Empirical results suggest that the number of change-points is larger than previously estimated in these series and the implied model is similar to a TVP (with stochastic volatility) model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting Time Series Subject to Multiple Structural Breaks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2006/041-hashempesaranforecastingtimeseries2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2006/041-hashempesaranforecastingtimeseries2006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper provides a new approach to forecasting time series that are subject to discrete structural breaks. We propose a Bayesian estimation and prediction procedure that allows for the possibility of new breaks occurring over the forecast horizon, taking account of the size and duration of past breaks (if any) by means of a hierarchical hidden Markov chain model. Predictions are formed by integrating over the parameters from the meta-distribution that characterizes the stochastic break-point process. In an application to U.S. Treasury bill rates, we find that the method leads to better out-of-sample forecasts than a range of alternative methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Spectral Tests for Conditional Mean Models in Time Series with Conditional Heteroscedasticity of Unknown Form</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2005/021-honggeneralizedspectraltests2005/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>econ.learning.resources@gmail.com (Econ Notes)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/papers/top5-restud/restud-2005/021-honggeneralizedspectraltests2005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading-element&#34; id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/span&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;#abstract&#34; class=&#34;heading-mark&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;    &lt;svg class=&#34;octicon octicon-link&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 16 16&#34; version=&#34;1.1&#34; width=&#34;16&#34; height=&#34;16&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;path d=&#34;m7.775 3.275 1.25-1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1 4.95 4.95l-2.5 2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1-4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l2.5-2.5a2.002 2.002 0 0 0-2.83-2.83l-1.25 1.25a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042Zm-4.69 9.64a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 2.83 0l1.25-1.25a.751.751 0 0 1 1.042.018.751.751 0 0 1 .018 1.042l-1.25 1.25a3.5 3.5 0 1 1-4.95-4.95l2.5-2.5a3.5 3.5 0 0 1 4.95 0 .751.751 0 0 1-.018 1.042.751.751 0 0 1-1.042.018 1.998 1.998 0 0 0-2.83 0l-2.5 2.5a1.998 1.998 0 0 0 0 2.83Z&#34;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Economic theories in time series contexts usually have implications on and only on the conditional mean dynamics of underlying economic variables. We propose a new class of specification tests for time series conditional mean models, where the dimension of the conditioning information set may be infinite. Both linear and nonlinear conditional mean specifications are covered. The tests can detect a wide range of model misspecifications in mean while being robust to conditional heteroscedasticity and higher order time-varying moments of unknown form. They check a large number of lags, but naturally discount higher order lags, which is consistent with the stylized fact that economic behaviours are more affected by the recent past events than by the remote past events. No specific estimation method is required, and the tests have the appealing “nuisance parameter free” property that parameter estimation uncertainty has no impact on the limit distribution of the tests. A simulation study shows that it is important to take into account the impact of conditional heteroscedasticity; failure to do so will cause overrejection of a correct conditional mean model. In a horse race competition on testing linearity in mean, our tests have omnibus and robust power against a variety of alternatives relative to some existing tests. In an application, we find that after removing significant but possibly spurious autocorrelations due to nonsynchronous trading, there still exists significant predictable nonlinearity in mean for S&amp;amp;P 500 and NASDAQ daily returns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
